Guide to the Wesley Works archive, 1676-1996 and undated, bulk 1724-1791, 1960-1996 RL.01368
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Bibliography Series (Volumes 33-34), 1710-1791, 1841, 1947-1993 and undated, 10 boxes
  - Stemmata and Texts Subseries, 1733-1759 and circa 1960s-1980s
    - 2-3. Norris, John: A Treatise on Christian Prudence (Green/UC 2) and Reflections Upon the Conduct of Human Life (Green/UC 25) (1734) (Box 98)
      Materials are mainly about the Treatise.
    - 4. (Green/UC 26) The Christian Pattern (1735) (Box 98)
    - 5. (Green 4) Advice to a Young Clergyman (1735) (Box 98)
    - 6. (Green/UC 5) A Sermon Preached at St. Mary's in Oxford (1735) [no folder for this item in sequence] (Box 98)
    - 7. (excluded from Green) Dissertationes in Librum Jobi by Samuel Wesley (1736) (Box 98)
    - 8. (Green/UC 6) A Collection of Psalms and Hymns (1737) (Box 98)
    - 9. (Green/UC 7) A Collection of Psalms and Hymns (1738) (Box 98)
    - 10. (Green/UC 8) A Sermon on Salvation By Faith (1738) (Box 98)
    - 11. (Green/UC 9) Doctrine of Salvation, Faith, and Good Works (1738) (Box 98)
    - 12. (Green/UC 10) An Abstract/Extract on the Life of Halyburton (1739) (Box 98)
    - 13. (Green/UC 15) Hymns and Sacred Poems (1739) (Box 98)
    - 14. (Green/UC 11) Free Grace (1739) (Box 98)
    - 15. (Green/UC 12) Nicodemus, by A. Francke (1739) (Box 98)
    - 16. (Green/UC 14) Two Treatises, by R. Barnes, 1739) (Box 98)
    - 17, 18. (UC 18B, UC18A) The Means of Grace, by Charles Wesley (1740); and The Life of Faith, by Charles Wesley (1740) (Box 98)
    - 19. (Green/UC 13) Journal, Extract I (1735-8), and 19.i. (Williams' affid), 1740) (Box 98)
    - 20-39. Journal, Extracts, 1740-1791) (Box 98)
      Note: individual correspondences between these twenty items and their numbering in the Green bibliography is too complex to be listed here. See folder for this information.
    - 40. (Green/UC 19) Hymns and Sacred Poems (1740) (Box 98)
    - 41. (Green/UC 17) Nature and Design of Christianity (1740) (Box 98)
    - 42. (Green/UC 16) Serious Considerations Concerning the Doctrines of Election and Reprobation (1740) (Box 98)
    - 43. (Green/UC 21) Extract of the Life of M. de Renty (1741) (Box 98)
    - 44. (Green/UC 30) A Collection of Psalms and Hymns (1741) (Box 98)
    - 45. (Green/UC 26) Extract of The Christian's Pattern (1741) (Box 98)
    - 46-47. (Green/UC 31-32) Hymns on God's Everlasting Love (1741) (Box 98)
    - 48. (Green/UC 22) Serious Considerations on Absolute Predestination (1741) (Box 99)
    - 49. (Green/UC 24) A Dialogue Between a Predestinarian and His Friend (1741) [no folder for this item in sequence] (Box 99)
    - 50. (Green/UC 24) The Almost Christian (1741) (Box 99)
    - 51. (Green/UC 27) The Scripture Doctrine Concerning Predestination, Election, and Reprobation, 1741) (Box 99)
    - 52. (Green/UC 23) A Short Account of the Death of Mrs. Hannah Richardson (1741) (Box 99)
    - 53. (Green/UC 29) Christian Perfection (1741) (Box 99)
    - 54. (Green/UC 40) Hymns and Sacred Poems (1742) (Box 99)
    - 56. (UC 33A) Whole Armour of God (1742) (Box 99)
    - 58. (UC 32A) The Taking of Jericho (1742) (Box 99)
    - 59. (Green/UC 33) Awake Thou That Sleepest, CW, 1742) (Box 99)
    - 60. (UC 39) Elegy on the Death of Robert Jones (1742) (Box 99)
    - 61. (UC 40A) A Sermon Preached... by the Reverend Henry Piers (1742) (Box 99)
    - 62. (UC 41A) Letter to Capt. Robert Williams (1742) (Box 99)
    - 63. (UC 40C) Some Remarks on the letter from Rev. Mr. Whitefield to Wesley, by Susanna Wesley, 1742) (Box 99)
    - 64. (UC 19.i) The Fourteenth Chapter of Isaiah (1742) (Box 99)
    - 65. (UC 40D) A Thanksgiving for the Colliers (1742) (Box 99)
    - 66. (UC 41B) A Second Letter to... Williams (1742) (Box 99)
    - 67. (Green/UC 35) The Principles of a Methodist, by Josiah Tucker, 1742) (Box 99)
    - 68. (Green/UC 41) A Collection of Hymns... from Hymns and Sacred Poems (1742) (Box 99)
    - 69. (Green/UC 38) A Collection of Tunes (1742) (Box 99)
    - 70. (UC 41B) A Hymn for Condemned Prisoners (1742) (Box 99)
    - 71. (Green/UC 42) Thoughts on Marriage and a Single Life (1743) (Box 99)
    - 72. (Green/UC 44) Word in Season: Advice to Soldier (1743) (Box 99)
    - 73. (Green/UC 43) Nature, Design, and General Rules (1743) (Box 99)
    - 74. (Green/UC 47) An Earnest Appeal... 1743) (Box 99)
    - 75. (UC 47A) A Letter From a Private Person (1743) (Box 99)
    - 76. (UC 47B) Letter from a Late Roman Catholic (1743) (Box 99)
    - 77. (Green/UC 45) A Practical Treatise on Christian Perfection (1743) (Box 99)
    - 78. (Green/UC 58) A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems (1744) (Box 99)
    - 79. (Green/UC 46) The Pilgrim's Progress, by Bunyan, 1743) (Box 99)
    - 80. (UC 47C) Hymn for Christmas Day (1743) [no folder for this item in sequence] (Box 99)
    - 81. (Green/UC 57) Rules of the Band Societies (1744) (Box 99)
    - 82., 83. (Green/UC 60, 59) Hymns for Times of Trouble, Hymns for Times of Persecution (1744) (Box 99)
    - 84. A Brief Account of a Late Trial (1744) (Box 100)
    - 85. (Green/UC 54) Narrative of the Late Work of God (1744) (Box 100)
    - 86. (Green/UC 48) A Serious Call to a Holy Life (1744) (Box 100)
    - 87. (Green/UC 74) A Collection of Prayers for Families (1744) (Box 100)
    - 88. (Green/UC 49) The Distinguishing Marks of a Work of the Spirit of God (1744) (Box 100)
    - 90. (Green/UC 50) Extract of Zizendorf's Discourses (1744) (Box 100)
    - 93. (Green/UC 51) The Life of God in the Soul of Man (1744) (Box 100)
    - 94. (UC 84) Hymns for Christmas Day (1744) [no folder for this item in sequence] (Box 100)
    - 112. (Green/UC 84) Hymns for the Nativity of Our Lord (1745) (Box 100)
    - 116. (Green/UC 90) Hymns for Our Lord's Resurrection (1746) (Box 100)
    - 124. (Green/UC 94) Hymns on the Great Festivals (1746) (Box 100)
    - 134. (Green/UC 98) Graces Before Meat (1746) (Box 100)
    - 235. (Green/UC 190) The Case of the Unhappy People of Custrin (1759) (Box 100)
    - 631. Further Thoughts on Separation (1790) (Box 100)
    - 800-823. Proposals--brief notes, photocopies, and stemma for the projected item numbers 800-823 of the bibliography, 5 folders (Box 100)
  - Typescripts Subseries, circa 1960s-1991 and undated
    This subseries contains the most complete version Baker left of the two-volume bibliography for the Bicentennial Edition. The core of this version is a draft he completed in 1981 and distributed to other project editors and scholars. More than 700 pages long, this manuscript contained Baker's essays and stemma for the first 106 titles in the Wesley bibliography (out of approximately 800 intended entries). To this version he added corrections and updated pages at various points in the 1980s and early 1990s. He then sent the 1991 version to the libraries of several universities participating in the WWEP (Drew, Emory, SMU, and Duke). This draft does not exactly match the list of individually foldered texts and stemma in the previous subseries. That list stops earlier, at item 94, but also picks up again with scattered higher-numbered entries in the bibliography.
    - Correspondence on drafts, introduction, and updates to bibliography, 1981-1991 (Box 100)
    - Contents, undated (Box 100)
    - Preliminary summaries, 1970-1981 (Box 100)
    - Summary/index, 1981 (Box 100)
    - Summary, edited photocopy, 1981 (Box 100)
    - Summary, 1990-1991 (Box 101)
    - Locations, 1983, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Undifferentiated items to check, undated (Box 101)
    - "A Descriptive and Analytical Bibliography": full draft of bibliography entries 1-106 circa 1981, with updates through 1991, 5 folders (Box 101)
    - Typescript with edits, 1981 and undated, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 101)
      Contains edited/updated pages only of the full draft above--i.e., the pages to have been inserted later into the 1981 version. All of these may already have been incorporated, but a full comparison has not been made.
    - Typescript with edits, 1981 and undated, Folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 102)
    - Wesley Checklist, circa 1960s (Box 102)
      Early version of a bibliography, listing some 400 citations and heavily annotated by FB.
    - Early compilation of a Wesley Bibliography, 1967, 2 folders (Box 103)
- Index and Miscellanea Series (Volume 35), 1968-1996
  The Index and Miscellanea Series contains a small amount of material for the concluding volume of the Bicentennial Edition, not to be published until all the other volumes are complete. As well as providing a general index to the entire set, this volume will also present background materials that explain rationales the editors used to decide for or against modernization of diction, spelling, punctuation, and many other issues involved in faithfully presenting Wesley's texts to a modern audience.
  Consists of correspondence and notes, mainly between Baker and John Vickers, about the contents of the index and indexing procedures. Vickers is the editor of this comprehensive index as well as the indexes for many of the individual units of the Bicentennial Edition, and some of the discussion here is about indexes for specific volumes. Arrangement is roughly chronological, although not to the item level.
  - Correspondence and procedures, 1968-1996, 5 folders (Box 102)
- General Files Series, 1755-1785, 1950-1995 and undated, 9 boxes
  Alphabetically arranged in various categories, the General Files contain material that does not belong under the heading of a single unit. Much of this includes correspondence, manuals, guidelines, bulletins, illustrations, and financial, and organization records of the Wesley Works Project. Also housed here is various Wesley materials excluded from the set, including his Old Testament Explanatory Notes.
  - Board of Directors and conferences, 1965-1992
    Includes meetings, conferences, and miscellaneous files about the project's archives and bylaws.
    - Archival guidelines, bylaws, incorporation, personnel, prospectus, and other general files, 1977-1992, 4 folders (Box 104)
    - Meetings and conferences, including 1969 (Dallas), 1974 (England), 1976, 1980 (England), 1982, 1985, Folders 1-12 of 17 (Box 104)
    - Meetings and conferences, including 1969 (Dallas), 1974 (England), 1976, 1980 (England), 1982, 1985, Folders 13-17 of 17 (Box 105)
  - Bulletins of the Wesley Works Project, 1969-1978
    Periodic bulletins, written mainly by Baker from the late 1960s through the late 1970s, updating board members and editors on overall progress of the project and decisions taken about various units, volumes, and topics.
    - Bulletins 1-15 and other documents, 1969-1978, 4 folders (Box 105)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1995
    Mixture of chronological correspondence folders, on general topics, and a few folders of correspondence with specific editors and publishers.
    - Leary, 1979 (Box 106)
    - Chronological, 1971-1995, 3 folders (Box 105)
    - Cragg, re: doctrinal appeals, 1973 (Box 106)
    - Early planning, 1975-1979 (Box 106)
    - Oxford University Press, 1969-1975 (Box 106)
    - General correspondence with editors, 14 folders (Box 121)
  - Editorial Board, 1964-1986
    Consists mainly of meetings and minutes of the editors, variously referred to as the Committee or the Board; a mix of unique information and information that overlaps with other categories, especially Board of Directors, Bulletins, and Editorial Procedures.
    - Chronological, 1964-1986, Folders 1-9 of 10 (Box 106)
    - Chronological, 1964-1986, Folder 10 of 10 (Box 107)
  - Editorial procedures, 1950-1995 and undated
    Extensive files on all aspects of editorial policy and procedures, from general copy editing guidelines to specific criteria for editing 18th century writing and Wesley's in particular. Contains Baker's short internal memorandum/essay, "Safeguarding Wesley's Style," 1989 (various versions of which also appear in other series).
    - Abbreviations, undated (Box 107)
    - Copy-editing, 1970-1980, and undated, 2 folders (Box 107)
    - Copy text, 1950-1971, and undated, 4 folders (Box 107)
    - Editing conventions (classical), 1970-1979 (Box 107)
    - Editing texts, 1950, 1955 (Box 107)
    - Editing Wesley, 1976 and undated (Box 107)
    - Editorial procedure, 1965-1986, 2 folders (Box 107)
    - Manual for locations and content, 1989 (Box 107)
    - Manual for workers, 1978 (Box 107)
    - Manual: notes on style, undated (Box 107)
    - Style guides, 1964-1995 and undated, 16 folders (Box 107-108)
  - Finances, 1960-1994
    - Advance orders, 1974-1975 (Box 109)
    - Expenses, 1971 and undated (Box 109)
    - Finance, 1984-1980 (Box 109)
    - Finance: budget, 1960-1980 (Box 109)
    - 1994 sales, finances, directors, unit editors, 1994 (Box 109)
    - Honorarium, 1987 (Box 109)
    - IRS, 1975-1978 (Box 109)
    - NEH Grants, 1980 (Box 109)
    - Returns--Abingdon and Oxford, 1979-1994, 2 folders (Box 109)
    - Sales to workers, 1976, 1980-1987 (Box 109)
    - Budgets, 1971-1977, travel expenses, and correspondence with donors, 25 folders (Box 121)
  - Illustrations, 1755-1785, 1978-1986 and undated
    Consists mainly of photographic prints, photocopies, and correspondence regarding illustrations and plates for various volumes.
    - Grids, undated (Box 109)
    - Vol. 1, 1755-1785, 1978 and undated (Box 109)
    - Vol. 1, 2, 1979, 1983 and undated (Box 109)
    - Vol. 1-4, 1979-1985 and undated (Box 109)
    - Vol. 7, 26, undated (Box 109)
    - Vol. 9, 1986 (Box 109)
    - Volumes 25-31, 1757, 1758, 1774, 1775, 1785 (Box 109)
  - Project outlines and summaries, 1961-1985
    - Early classification and Baker's appointment as Associate Editor and Archivist, 1961-1964 (Box 110)
    - Early plans and correspondence, 1961-1969, 2 folders (Box 110)
    - General statement, 1961, 1972-1979 (Box 110)
    - Outlines of volumes, 1978 (Box 110)
    - Projections, 1976-1978 (Box 110)
    - Summary of contents, 1970-1981 (Box 110)
    - Summary of WWP, 1985 (Box 110)
  - Publishers, 1960-1994
    - Abingdon Press, 1987-1989 (Box 111)
    - Oxford to Abingdon, 1982-1984 (Box 111)
    - Photo typesetting, 1980-1981 (Box 111)
    - Promotion, 1960-1988, 3 folders (Box 111)
    - Publication correspondence, 1974-1986, 3 folders (Box 111)
    - Reviews, 1976, 1983, 1984, and undated (Box 111)
    - Spanish: Obras de Wesley, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 111)
  - Research--various topics, 1964-1979 and undated
    Research notes on miscellaneous topics about JW and his writings, including material not used for the Bicentennial Edition, annotated photocopies of his Explanatory Notes Upon the Old Testament.
    - Hebrew of J.W., undated (Box 111)
    - OT Explanatory notes, 1964-1979 and undated (Box 111)
    - OT Explanatory noted--photocopies, undated, 3 folders (Box 103)
      Notes of JW not used for the Bicentennial Edition; it is a collated series of notes from Henry, Poole, and Wesley himself.
    - Quotations, 1971-1979, 2 folders (Box 111)
    - Research needed, undated (Box 111)
    - Xeroxes, undated (Box 111)
  - Uncategorized files, 1963-1993 and undated, 21 folders
    Single files on a variety of topics, including consultants, incorporation, project personnel, sponsors, reports by the textual editor, and a small amount of additional materials for the Social/Political Tracts and Journals units.
    - Additional materials: Theological treatises (Vol. 12) and Journals, 1979-1988, 2 folders (Box 111)
    - Consultants, incorporation, project personnel, information for and about sponsors, reports of the Textual Editor, and other files, 1963-1993 and undated, 19 folders (Box 112)
  - Reference materials, 1966 and undated; 1 Box
    Reference materials used in the editorial office.
    - Bibliography, undated; 13 folders folders (Box 122)
    - Stemmata, edns, undated; 2 folders (Box 122)
    - A Union Catalog of the publications of John and Charles Wesley, 1966 (Box 122)